software engineering radio episode 80
hours Jai with Peter Queens and VJ
heartbreak
[Music]
hello listeners this is Marcus just two
quick comments before we get started
with the actual content of the episode
the OSGi stuff stuff with bump and
Martine first of all remember we are
still running our experiment where we
want to see whether we can we can get
enough donations so we can keep the
thing going without any well support
sponsoring advertisement over you
whatever you would like to call this so
please go ahead and and donate if you
think that's that's worth it
the other thing is that recently in a
previous episode I promised this thing
about running an interactive episode
with listener feedback and being able to
call in I didn't forget it but actually
we don't have the time right now to do
it and we're focusing on our core
competency so we keep it on the radar
we'll do it at some point but we're too
busy right now with stuff outside of se
radio we all have a real life beyond the
podcast so that was all I wanted to say
now have fun with OSGi and stuff in this
episode we will talk about ours GI and
band and I are on the micros and we have
two guests invited and maybe those
guests can introduce themselves so Peter
would you start yes I'm Peter Queens
have been involved in the LGI since day
one I'm currently the OCI technical
director and the OCI evangelist great
and BJ would you introduce yourself
okay hi my name is BJ Hargrave I work
for IBM and the Lotus division and I've
been involved with those Jason's day too
Peter got there before me yes we've been
both working on Shea for some time we've
worked on unreleased one and two and
three and four and now we're up to 4.1
and so I currently chair the core
platform expert group at OSGi which does
the sort of central technology of the
the USGS specification and I also
currently hold the role of a chief
technical officer for the OSGi Alliance
okay great thank you so can can you can
you explain as what what is OSGi
yeah you wanted to do honors yeah sure
I'll start so basically OSGi is a if you
will a layer that you can run on top of
a java virtual machine and it fills in
some gaps that are really missing in
normal Java right in Java you can write
your code and you can have a bunch of
jha you can package them up in jars and
you can put all those jars in a class
path but basically there's no
information hiding you're no
encapsulation between those jars
anything and that's publicly accessible
and one jar can be loaded and used by
something in another jar and when you
get to large and more complex
applications you really need you know an
additional layer of information hiding
your encapsulations OSGi basically
provides that for you at the OSU
community event last week somebody
coined the term class letters on
steroids which I guess is a sort of sort
of humorous way to think of OSGi but it
really does give it defines a a regular
eyes class loader methodology where each
jar file which we call a bundle a twist
GI has the means to control which parts
of itself it wishes to share and make
visible to other jars and so you really
have the ability to decide there's a
programmer which parts of your jar or
the public API and which parts are just
private implementation details and so
that's sort of at the basic level one of
the main value propositions vhost yeah
but it provides more than that as well
in addition to that sort of what we call
the module layer osj also provides a a
lifecycle layer so that you can actually
install and uninstall and update these
modules into a running virtual machine
without requiring it to be restarted so
that's pretty powerful too and the final
thing we have is a service layer so in
addition to all these other capabilities
and which are fully dynamic we have a a
service-oriented architecture layer for
the virtual machines so one one bundle
can register a service other bundles can
then find that service and then
ultimately bind to the service and use
it so it provides a very nice and
elegant means for these bundles to share
objects between
cells using a nice service-oriented
model so they don't have to be coupled
to the implementation details of a
service they just have to know how to
look it up via some contract which in
the other studio which java world is a
Java interface and I think the key
things is the dynamics of this all it
really keeps on working even though
you're under install and uninstall
applications all in a single VM and it's
it's a very elegant model to write small
large applications that that need some
kind of extension model okay I think
somewhere on the website
I read that OSGi is a service-oriented
dynamic module system or component model
for Java so I think that emphasizes that
right yeah that's the tagline we're
using now the dynamic module system for
Java so it really gives you those
modularity features but as Peter
observed one of the key sort of values
and differentiator of OSGi over other
techniques is OSGi is fully dynamic
sorted from top to bottom and that's
very powerful too okay so I'm getting a
bit more elaborate what dynamic means so
you have different bundles or components
and then you have different services
provided by that components what means
dynamic in that context okay the the key
thing about the dynamic thing is that if
you have a bundle a bundle gets
installed there are primitives to to
install a bundle a jar file in the VM
and there are primitives to uninstall
the jar file from the VM so it will not
become it's not load no longer available
in the VM once a bundle is in the VM it
can be started which means it will get a
chance to run we will call some code in
the jar file and then it gets a chance
to register services and those are the
objects that are available to other
bundles when the bundle is stopped it's
no longer available the framework will
automatically unregistered all its
services and they're no longer available
to the other bundles and they should
remove any references to those service
objects with that model which in a way
is quite simple and elegant you can map
a lot of different patterns that are
dynamic the key example that I always
have is let's say that you make a
Bluetooth driver then when there is a
Bluetooth phone in the neighborhood you
register Bluetooth surface in the LGI
service registry then any bundle that is
interested in a Bluetooth device sees
hey there is a new Bluetooth service
picks it up and uses it until it gets an
event that that service is no longer
available and there are a lot of
different things that can be mapped to
that dynamic model for example you have
a communication interface as long as the
communication is up and running that
service is available if the
communication goes down the service
becomes unavailable
so by taking that dynamic very see the
dynamic city very serious and building
it into the base platform you're ready
to handle a lot of problems that are
normally quite complicated to handle and
I usually handle quite specifically in
in software right and the fact that we
engineered the Dyna Missa tee into the
entire system from the get-go is very
important to because it's not just one
layer that's understanding it it's all a
layer so as a bundle is uninstalled
right which removes it from the module
its lifecycle has changed it's removed
from the module system and from the
service layer all in one hit so this
really removes a lot of details from the
programmer because it's all handled form
by the framework right the key thing is
that we took these Dynamis 'ti actually
it was kind of funny because do you guys
remember Windows 95 heard of it well
well these guys are younger than we are
I think so Windows 95 was famous for for
rebooting you could change the tiniest
little configuration parameter and then
you had to reboot and it was really
annoying and Windows 95 was quite
popular when we got started in Windows
98 which had the same problem and the
mantra in the beginning was no reboot so
if you look at how is the I it's not
just the the framework that is dynamic
and as BJ said dynamic from from the
ground up all the services are dynamic
as well if you change the configuration
parameter it's automatically forwarded
to the interested parties there's only
one way to get configuration data and
that is the dynamic model so we've
really tried to take dynamics very
seriously and and interestingly in the
beginning we were scolded for that
because people said art is too
complicated and programmers can handle
that and and
that's too complicated and what we see
now by taking the dynamics into the
architecture from day one we have a huge
advantage over other systems because so
many things today are dynamic but you
still as a programmer of using just
using those you still need to be aware
of that the system is dynamic and you
need to take care how you write panels
that they be and behave nicely in the
dynamic environment yeah that's true and
I think that if you if you wrote only to
the sort of the raw basic OS JPI you
might have a lot more work to do to
really handle things well but we've
tried to provide other abstractions to
simplify that for the programmable to be
honest we we didn't do that in the
beginning we were taught that by others
and certainly as early as release two we
introduced the service tracker right so
it was observed and released one that
this is very hard and so when released
two we had the service tracker which
basically was a utility class - nicely
capture all of a management of at the
service layer the dynamism of services
being published and unpublished and
handling all that and also more recently
in release for we've seen things like
these
dependency injection frameworks on OSGi
which further simplify the model things
like OSGi zone declared services things
like this the spring or SGI project
that's going on now and there's other
things too like iPod you and Felix so
there's quite a number of different sort
of abstractions to ease the burden for
the programmer in dealing with OSGi is
Dyna Missa tee mm-hmm but sometimes if I
talk to people about OSGi and they think
about the dynamic behavior of OCI that
somehow objects in memory are
automatically collected or deleted or
updated or whatever and if I understand
LJ correctly this this is not the case
isn't it
no oh yeah I just relies upon normal
Java garbage collection it runs on pure
Java so there's nothing sort of magical
about it it really requires you know you
to do a good job managing references to
objects if you want them
removed and so even though you can sort
of uninstall a bundle the framework
itself takes care to release its
references to things in that bundle such
as its class loaders and class objects
that are any other objects such as
services but if somebody else happens to
be holding one of those references then
the garbage collector is not going to be
able to do its job mm-hmm
so I need to take care that they die for
example cut those references myself if
another bundle that I'm using goes away
right yeah so if you the bundle has a
service and you're using it you get the
service event to release it it's in
everyone's best interest for you to
dereference that service object but
that's I think where the value of these
subsystems like declarative services
iphoto service buying a spring IOC I
come in they take care of that okay so
maybe we can elaborate on that a bit
later I want to come bit back to the
basics of OSGi so where does Oscar I
come from and nowadays we're we're
hearing a lot about cirlces are so to 91
and to 94 to 77 maybe you can say
something about that sure the OSGi
started out as the work of several
companies back in 1998 I believe
Peterson fell very early on he was
consulting for Ericsson at the time and
that basically the team of people was
interested in trying to solve the
problem of the forthcoming residential
gateway in terms of providing a platform
neutral environment for deploying
services onto it and so ultimately the
work that came out of it was temporarily
jsr eight but ultimately went into a new
nonprofit democratic standards group
which we now call the OSGi alliance and
continued from there so release one was
put out and I think it was 2000 and then
we've now up to 2007 so we've had you
know seven years and and former four
major releases have been put out so
we've had a lot of history there it's
quite try to be the maturity in then how
it is oh yeah definitely so I mean and
then if you talk about the other jsr is
that you mentioned
I think it was last year before we
started jsr 232 that was a Java ME jsr
and that was about bringing a more
advanced Java platform to the mobile
phone space at that time all the mobile
phones were pretty much running CL DC
with mid P and there was a perceived
need that a more advanced environment
was going to be needed for future phones
and so SGI was looked at as that
environment and so we in addition to
starting a mobile expert group in OSGi
to work on that effort simultaneously
jsr 232 was formed by Nokia and Motorola
2 also within the JCP process created
jsr to also capture that specification
and so that went final subsequent to
that we also started jsr 291 for similar
reasons to bring the OSGi specification
to the Java SE space and also around
that you mentioned I think it was 277
and 294 which are also related Sun as
the was the speculated on both of those
GS ours 277 is also looking at an e
module layer for Java similar to what
OSGi provides and 294 is a language jsr
looking at adding some I think some
additional capabilities at the language
level around information hiding to
address some problems that exist so
those are the I think that's sort of the
basic landscape for the set of jsr that
are out there I think the the goals of
jsr 277 are slightly different than I
was shining that they're mostly looking
at a static model versus OSGi which is
very much focused on it was always
delivered a dynamic model and the other
thing about 277 is that there that their
intent is to sort of provide it as a
basic poor basic part of Java 7 and
whenever whenever that comes out I think
it's 2008 or something so there are some
issues to be dealt with there and I know
peter has as well known as has got a
very popular blog entry he wrote
detailing some of his criticisms of the
early draft at 277
okay so 294 is
all the super packages jsr chest - yes
yes it's basically a language construct
to define molarity in the language okay
so can you say that 294 and 277 together
are always g9o so this you can packages
in the Java system those jr's have made
some effort to separate themselves in
that they or they each have a goal to
operate without the other so I think
certainly from 294 is they've been
pretty explicit that 294 should function
in the absence of a module system and I
believe I'm not sure but I think the
same is true of 277 and that it doesn't
require 294
but clearly they'll want to work
together but without necessarily
requiring each other so in that case the
sum total doesn't equal oh absolutely
not - 94 is just a language construct so
if that comes out and OSI I was
supported 100% and that that will be
transparent at 277 that is a huge
overlap that is 277 has a repository
that OSD I kept out of the specification
and they included and on a module layer
as Beatty said they're addressing the
same problem but they do it in a way
that is in my opinion a bit
disappointing because it's it's even
less than our release 1 but they're
addressing with their dependency model
the dependency bottle is pretty poor ok
I was just just for Java right or are
there other implementations for other
languages no our CI is grown up with
Java we we leverage a ver - to a large
extent so currently there is a real need
for the Java VM at the bottom however we
are talking currently in the enterprise
expert group to allow our CI
applications to more easily talk to
other environments like dotnet and there
is an effort which with the working
title universe allows the I but we have
to find another title for that which
will allow you to integrate applications
OCI applications but they can actually
run in another execution environment so
you will have a similar or equal
management model
and you will able to talk to them but
that that is still very early work there
is no no concrete evidence of this
visible but that's one of the things
we're talking about we'd really like to
communicate with those other
environments and integrate it more
closely rye toast yeah really
I mean it's built on top of the of the
back of the great dynamic nature of Java
and so we exploit that to the nth degree
which is one of the reasons OSGi is it
can be so dynamic and some of these
other environments of course - to a
lesser degree have the ability to
support that level of dynamic so it's
hard to sort of map 100% of OS J's
capabilities on to other environments
and of course you can go to environments
like C and C++ you have the whole
security issue so what what do you think
where where does OSGi where's the future
of us G I so I heard a lot about these
mobile phones and embedded devices and I
also read something about the enterprise
expert group so it sounds more like the
G I'm moving towards server-side
application server area whatever so can
can you can you give us some in some
insights yeah the term I really like is
Universal middleware if you look at how
we build applications nowadays and you
see the more and more component I see
the open source movement has brought us
some tremendous value by delivering
large subsystems where we built our
applications on however if you look
today how these things need to be
integrated then you find that it is not
always that easy and they don't really
always match up very well I think that's
really the the where our I can play an
intermediate role if you follow if you
deliver your your code as OCI bundles
then they will work together through the
service registry so the boundaries
between these different subsystems is is
much much much better defined than in
normal Java where you cannot hide any
packages so your implementation code is
just as visible as your API that you
want to expose there is no dynamism that
if you have certain things a plug-in
there's no plug-in model in Java that
works very elegantly and the OCI is
basically a big plugin model so I like
the word Universal middleware because it
describes this idea that you have
middleware that will run anywhere from a
mobile phone
up to an enterprise server which is
becoming more and more important because
many enterprise applications or
enterprise enterprises want to make
software that runs for example on the
server but also in the mobile phone so
you can run your business logic in
different places right we had a very
interesting presentation in Germany last
week where there was a company that
actually did that they had a possibility
to edit the the configuration parameters
of a device in the network and they
could move that code without the I
bundles to different clients right so
the fact that you know she is we
mentioned before comes from an embedded
heritage which is actually is a value
point as we move into the enterprise
space because it's already small and
lean and it's always easy to move up but
it's always hard to move down so I think
that you know in terms of the future of
a shy it's gonna be I think a valuable
technology no matter where are you
deploying Java all right as long as you
can as long as you're not see LDC you
basically can run on any job environment
and the values there they're important
to everybody writing Java code right and
I think that the big thing is it will
allow you to know if it will run or not
the big thing with Java is of course you
can write a piece of code it runs on all
these different environments but the
metadata is not defined in standard Java
you don't have the the management system
that can decide well this will actually
run on that device or not and I think
that's really where all the AI comes in
it creates a complete well-defined
specification that allows you to deploy
that in all those different environments
in a reliable and a controlled way
sounds sounds pretty much like you can
use OSGi for any kind of java
application said right yeah if you can
run java OCI in in my mind is a
no-brainer right so any non-trivial java
application that's gets you know more
than one component to it is a perfect
opportunity to exploit OSGi and if you
take one of the open source
implementations like for
Felix that's only 250 K so we're talking
about a relatively small layer that
gives in an incredible advantage for
reliability in the ease of software
development we had a guy from BA on a
previous conference and he said that we
thought we were working modular until we
started using our CI and then they found
out that they had lots of coupling that
they were not really aware of and they
found out that using our CI how to do
this better can you give us examples
where with G is already used today I
guess the most popular example that
everyone knows of it I think is eclipse
right
Louis J is the plug-in model for Eclipse
when they went to release three they
they were able to successfully perform
open-heart surgery discard their sort of
bespoke component model and then start
OSGi in and so everyone it runs Eclipse
you know whether it's the IDE or any
other Eclipse application today they're
using OSGi right in there well and then
of course we've got B EA with the micro
kernel architecture a JBoss that changed
that micro container to support ozi that
is a IBM websphere right there's a lot
of work going on in the enterprise space
certainly people are moving to it
there's a lot you know it's I think a
lot of people are using it it's not so
well known in certain applications but
it certainly is being used in more more
places I think but it certainly eclipse
is the most obvious and sort of very
well publicized exists to be again but
as Peter observes yeah speed observes
people are starting to use it in
enterprise software like the EA if
they're MSA architecture you know they
just released a new product I think it's
called WebLogic event server or
something like that and that's basically
a completely from the ground up you know
OSGi architected system they use their
MSA architecture and all the parts are
state models and plug into it so that's
very exciting and what for me is the
most exciting is that that I do quite a
bit of consultancy and you get into
companies that you never heard of and
they do the most fantastic things with
with OSD I I was at a company a couple
of months ago that we're doing x-ray
diffraction machines where they used
RFID to detect the components
that we use for the the diffraction
analysis they get a bundle depending on
the RFID and together they create the
system that that does its job
using the dynamics completely and all
the possibility of ozi and there are
hundreds or me maybe today even
thousands of companies that have a
relatively small market are not visible
but are applying our zi and and having a
great advantage with it okay it sounds
if you talk about is some kind of
middleware for for let's say every kind
of java application it sounds like there
might be conflict with existing
middleware components like application
servers or whatever and if i heard some
some kind of class loading and stuff
like that can you can you elaborate a
bit on this kind of how OSGi works
together with these kind of containers
and existing little wish stuff and stuff
like that well I think there's a couple
of ways you can think of it one is that
OSGi provides a platform for middleware
certainly and you see that when people
actually are implementing their their
application servers on top of OSGi you
know for example des i'ma say
architecture iBM has put out its
WebSphere application server that the
the products themselves are implemented
as a set of OSGi bundles and so that
really doesn't impact I think the class
loading structures of the applications
themselves but I think that's where the
next challenge comes and it's certainly
one of the areas that those GIS
Enterprise expert group is looking at is
you know you know for example like Java
EE defines basically a certain class
loader structure for the applications
deploying into and that's different than
the OSGi class learning model so there's
some certainly some areas where we in in
the you know the community OSGi and java
ee needs to look at how to make those
technologies work better together and
that is a major piece of work that the
enterprise expert groups got to look at
but interestingly if you're looking in
practice at the moment it works quite
well together a lot of people using our
CI in the bottom but actually there's a
server bridge that allows you to use our
CI
inside a application server so you can
use all the advantages of
osei and still get deployed in the
normal way in in a large-scale
application server so you can implement
your your enterprise javabean to web
applications and all those kind of of
server-side components using OSGi yeah
well I think there's a spring I was the
I project where the spring interphase 21
used osei or has built a specification
to use ozi in their framework which
allows you to use all the spring api's
to implement j2ee applications so
there's a lot of choice the thing is
that our CI if you look at it it doesn't
really do that much but it does it
terribly well and it tries not to touch
anything it's not supposed to touch
which means that you can combine it in
in an amazing number of ways and it
stays out of the way right I think the
spring ster is an example a great
example of that complimentary nature
right Spring Framework has been very
popular for some time and is gaining
popularity but you know they sort of
interfaces 21 started seeing requests
from their clients about how do I make
this work with OSGi because and I was
gee I was a complementary technology
provide the things that spring didn't
provide and I think the spring OSGi
project is going to be very interesting
for people to look at because they get
the benefits of spring and OSGi that
without really having to do anything
significant to their applications so the
main thing which spring or the
combination of spring Austria brings is
that you have a separation between your
components right and you can use one
component in several versions at the
same time yes yeah so you get the
benefits of the Earth Day modularity and
its ability to support multi versions
okay so there are two reasons why to
deploy and OSGi application the one
thing is the service related stuff and
the other thing is the component model
yes can you can you tell us a bit more
about these kind of different versions
deployed to the system so it sounds like
like you can deploy different version of
the same module in the same time or
updating from one version to the next
version
keeping the VM running said correct well
one of the you know as we were working
on the release for specification one of
the important requirements that came up
certainly in particular from the
enterprise space is the ability to have
a controlled migration you know from one
version to another so it's quite often
that people have deployed some
application it's composed of a set of
components and they want to deploy a new
application well if they want to share
one of these components they might have
an issue because these two different
applications for whatever reasons
require different versions of some
component that they have in common and
so we put support and release for to
enable a component to be deployed sort
of multiple times at different versions
so I can have you know component one
component a at version one and component
a at version two and then the the
information in the manifest that
controls how the OSGi framework does its
classloader
connections will wire up the
applications to the right version of the
component that they need and so you can
deploy then both applications at the
same time because the multi versioning
support lets that happen and this is
actually implemented in in the available
open source project right now yes yeah
because it's released for it's a
requirement for release for okay yeah so
that's available you know and all the
open source Equinox Felix can apple or
fish they all support this Multi
versioning support and it is really
important because in the industry as I
said earlier we're getting more and more
open source projects that that we take
from the net and we put in our
applications and these are open source
projects not always require the same
version so with OC I you can actually
still use libraries for example you need
hibernate but one subsystem requires
hibernate to any other requires
hibernate tree and they can actually
just reside in the same VM and on a
certain level collaborate even though
they will use different hibernates in
the bottom but but can they can they
share share objects between each other
as long as well as long as they're not
from the same from hibernate for example
if one applicant gets a hibernate to
object and passes it to it the other
application which is wired to hibernate
3 they'll get a class cast exception so
Peter said you know as long as they're
just using hibernate at the lower
portion of the application and they
share higher level abstractions that's
fine all right but you know you still
have issues you know there's no magic
here it's just that if you have a class
object it needs to be need to be shared
by the same or created by the same class
learner if you want to share them across
to the applications but that's why it's
also important that or that's why the
service layer is very important because
the service layer it is completely aware
of these issues and if you have a
service object in a service registry and
it happens to be not consistent with
your class base then you will not be
able to see it well you can see it but
you have to do some more work to see it
normally you will not see it so you can
only get wired up to services that are
compatible with your class base right so
there's another example of how all the
layers are nicely coupled together to
provide you know simplifying world views
for programmer it seems like OSGi makes
me think a lot more about these kind of
how-to componentize map application how
what what what types to make public what
types make private what types to share
between between components what what is
real published API and and at least
makes me think about more about the what
is the architecture of my system right
because it gives you an additional tool
above sort of the standard
object-oriented decapsulation you now
can actually encapsulate your components
and so that's really does make you think
more about how to properly organize your
components it's really that I've given a
lot of tutorials and courses and it's
really all they're always such a nice
few when people start to see what OSD is
they make the first bundle and then they
start to see the kind of tools they
suddenly get in something that is
extremely important for the normal work
and I've never really seen somebody
being put off by the overhead that you
inevitably have they always like this
this control that they suddenly get
about their own software and reuse so if
I'm if I'm going to start and write my
first SGI application today what are the
most common problems I'm going to run in
this is a good question you need to find
a good introduction and new Bartlett is
giving a very nice series on eclipse on
how to get started with our CI and I
think that's a good introduction my blog
this number of blogs out there like
Peter's blog and Glenn Normanton has a
blog and then the Chris Neil Bartlett's
so there's a number of people out there
giving you some introductory
introductory material and then it's just
a matter of finding some supporting
tools so you can get a clips it's got
some some support in there through the
PDE for Bundle programming peter kreen's
himself is released what he calls the B
and D tool and you can get that from his
website and it provides a sort of a nice
sort of low-level tool to package up
your mumbles and it gives a simplified
view of setting up your manifest so it's
pretty helpful for I think beginning
programmers time it's very the manifest
of course there's a lot of metadata
involved and being detailed basically
guesses and calculates the manifest data
in a very simple way it saves a lot of
work okay and so if I'm a bit more
experienced and have written my
HelloWorld bundle are there any other
problems I might run into so for example
can I use any kind of sir party library
without any problems no that I think
that's the biggest problem at the moment
if you are in a green field and our CI
is is absolutely without a doubt - no
brainer the problem is that because of
the fact that Java never really had a
good extension mechanism you see that a
lot of bigger subsystem have created
their own plugin systems and these
plugin systems are invariably based on
class loudest and most of these people
that wrote the plugin systems just solve
their own short term problem they didn't
really think about the bigger problem of
how you handle these different things
together right they also made
assumptions about the structure of the
class lists aren't that they're
hierarchical and some other things which
are different than the OSG is sort more
graph oriented arrangement so I think
it's not not so much as they use classes
that they made assumptions which were
sort of rather than limiting assumptions
well in anyway the defect that they were
building an extension model which means
that we have hundreds of different
extension models pollutes the whole
landscape and they're not always
compatible so you get incompatibilities
and we're currently working very hard
for these four four
the next release after this for that one
to see what we can do to make existing
libraries play nicer than they do today
but yeah that is definitely work
involved yes I think there is there's
two main issues I see in people moving
for example existing code onto OSGi one
is the this class letter should we
talked about people I think making
assumptions about the class learner
structure and and crankin doing their
own bespoke plug-in models and I think
that the sort of more difficult issue
which is frustrating to people is that
if they have a set of legacy code and
it's never been in a module system which
enforces much larren T they're altima
there's a lot of sort of spaghetti that
they have to tease apart and that can be
quite a bit of work and so I think
that's another major off-putting thing
that people have okay yeah the biggest
mistake you could make if you start with
our CI and you got your six and a
thousand line system and you think you
you're gonna break that up at forty
different bundles and be happy more
utilizing existing code is not always
easy okay so the modularity on the one
hand is an architectural thing which I
have to handle in my application the
class loader stuff is another problem
because most often it occurs in sir
party libraries right can I handle that
somehow or is it a show stuff usually
there are solutions and as I said in the
next release we're trying to find some
common answers to the problem so that it
will be easier to solve but one of the
nasty ones is hibernate and there are
solutions do that the the problem that I
find more is that some of the real if
you can make a grassroot application
then the OCI model allows you to do some
really really elegant things and the
existing libraries just don't really
play that well because they were grown
up in a more monolithic application
world so I also think it's just a matter
of time in a couple of years more and
more libraries will actually have
discovered this model and will have used
it and play nice in that that that more
modular world right hopefully is OSG
eight continues to be successful and
people continue to adopt it that over
time hopefully we'll see these
third-party libraries you know spend the
effort to make them so
work well in the earthships pace and
then this won't be as big an issue in
the future look at spring they adapted
all their library order at they are
adapting all their libraries to to play
nice in the OCI world so that will be
for the enterprise world pretty
important are there other things which
might occur or cause problems for
example you did the dynamics yeah well I
think the the things like I pojo and and
declarative services bring out yeah
basically take care of that problem
quite well of course you have to be be
aware of it but my experience is that
people actually love it because they see
that the real world out there is dynamic
it is a dynamic world and trying to make
a static program usually doesn't always
work that well in practice as well so I
think the dynamics are usually embraced
by the programmers as as something is
hey wow this is really cool and suddenly
a lot of dynamic things in the real
world can be mapped on the service model
the dynamic service model so they
usually take the the the OCI programming
model and and find patterns in the real
world that can be mapped very nicely so
I rarely hear people complaining about
it after they they have a basic grasp of
how it works yeah I think one other
certainly one other thing that needs to
be noticed is that you know if you're
writing these quote static programs
they're often reasonably single-threaded
and people don't have to worry so much
about thread safety but certainly in the
OSGi environment which is sort of very
dynamic you getting events they might
come in in different threads service
events etc and so it's you have to pay
more attention to the thread safety of
your code and I think in an OSGi world
and you might have to in a sort of a
more flat you know single threaded
static world and so these are some
little things that can can sort of bite
you later so it's important to always
you know this is true in general but
always to pay attention to the thread
safety of your code right but that is
really true in general because I think
most even the reasonably complicated
applications today use multiple
threading it's so it's very hard to do
without are there any kind of
applications you want right with the
OSGi well I'm having a problem there I'm
working on a command-line tool that
needs an extensibility model and I'm
I'd like to use our CI because I think
is the perfect plug-in model in the
world I just have to figure out if I can
start it up fast enough our eye starts
off quite quickly but for a command-line
tool you really want it to be able to
run immediately so I'm having to do some
tests to see if I can get it to run as
fast as a but that might be something
that just is a filter basically if you
don't have any extensibility at all and
the application is quite small yeah
don't use osei extensibility or you get
a more complicated system basically more
than and then ten twenty thirty thousand
lines of code then all Zi becomes
interesting well yeah I think it becomes
interesting the more components you have
right if you have a single component
system then a sort of pointless to have
a component model like OSGi but if you
have a set of components and you want to
come perhaps to compose them in a
variety of different ways you really
need a system like OSGi so if you know
if you look at these people like ba and
the IBM that are building their sort of
enterprise software out of it that
they're doing it sort of partly I think
to get the advantages of modularity but
also another significant value to them
is that they can recompose these
components into new products quickly
because they put the effort in upfront
to modular eyes and component eyes them
they can quickly respond to new market
opportunities and reassemble or set of
components with other components and
ship new products there's a very
interesting presentation from BA I think
it's still on the website of the Eclipse
con conference where the good the bad
and the ugly where they basically
outline all those advantages that they
had the huge monolithic application
servers of 30 40 megabytes and they
could bring it down to two sixes they
could make systems based on the
microarchitecture that was six or seven
megabytes so you get a lot more
flexibility when once you're
componentized
it's not always easy to get there but
once you are there there are a huge
number of advantages hey I think we are
pretty much done now have you forgot to
mention something well the thing is that
we touched upon it a little bit but I'd
like to make a call to the industry is
to take a good look at OSD AI and see if
you can support it if you make an
per source project the nice thing about
the OCI metadata is that it is very non
intrusive anoxia bundle is a nowadays it
is a normal Java Java file so it can be
used as you always used it but by taking
the time to see what you have to add the
component model becomes much more a
reality and I think the whole industry
has it as a tremendous advantage if we
get a good component model that group a
can make a set of components that I can
plug into my framework without having to
do a lot of work so yeah I'd like to
call out to the industry to to to ask
take a look what are you doing are you
making components that are usable for
other people
take a look at our CI and and at the
necessary metadata and if people have a
problem there that they need some help
and they can always contact me to to see
if I can help them or get them in touch
with the people that might be able to
help them in that area and we've got an
OS GI dev - to have mail lists that
people can get on to and you know all of
the is a whole bunch of people out there
that are osj skill can help answer
questions and provide advice and and
also to speak to Peter's point you know
if you look at his BND tool is a great
example of a single jar that is both an
a command line tool and OSGi bundle an
eclipse plugin I may even plug in all at
once so it's an an an Tosca loop and an
ant test so it's not impossible to write
your code to deploy you know in the
environments other than just OSGi and
yet still support the rst environment
cool so thank you very very much for
this interview
welcome got the question here thanks for
the chance thank you
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team @ s e - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Poli for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineer a do
website for details